<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods mercy and justice displayed, in the wicked life and penitential death of Dorothy Lillingstone executed the 7. of April, 1679. at Kennington, for murthering her bastard-childe. Published at her earnest request. With Allowance.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42940</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G960B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223686</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833972</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833972</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38451</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42940)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38451)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1831:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods mercy and justice displayed, in the wicked life and penitential death of Dorothy Lillingstone executed the 7. of April, 1679. at Kennington, for murthering her bastard-childe. Published at her earnest request. With Allowance.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J. Bennet, for R. Miller,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1: The life and death of Dorothy Lillingstone.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lillingstone, Dorothy, d. 1679 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38451:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Gods Mercy and Juſtice Diſplayed, IN THE WICKED LIFE AND PENITENTIAL DEATH OF <hi>DOROTHY LILLINGSTONE,</hi> Executed the 7. of <hi>April,</hi> 1679. at <hi>Kenning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> for Murthering her Baſtard-Childe.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed at Her Earneſt Requeſt.</p>
            <p>With Allowance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Bennet,</hi> for <hi>R. Miller.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:38451:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38451:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Life and Death of</hi> Dorothy Lillingſtone.</head>
            <p>I Acknowledge it a mercy beyond my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or deſert, that the Almighty ſhould pleaſe to ſpare me this time and opportunity, to make my peace with him, who by my repeated Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties I have ſo often and hainouſly offended, as likewiſe to confeſs my crimes to others, thereby to deter and warn all from treading in thoſe paths that have brought me into the condition I am now miſerably groaning under; the latter of which works, as it may conduce in ſome meaſure to accompliſh the former, is the intent of the inſuing lines; wherein to pretermit all matters unneceſſary, I ſhall in the firſt place give the world ſome account of my former ill-led life, and the crime for which I ſtand under ſentence of Death: and in the next, my preſent ſence of the ſtate and condition I am in: As to the firſt of which, I am to acquaint you, That I was born in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> and received my Education under godly and religious pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, whoſe names in reſpect to the reverence I owe to their memory, I ſhall in this place ſpare; with them till the age of thirteen years I lived, in which ſpace (the moſt innocent part of my life, I can reflect upon) I began to find the ſprouting of thoſe Sins which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in my life and future converſation, did grow to greater maturity, and bore the bitter fruits of my preſent ſufferings: The firſt of which that came under
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38451:3"/>my obſervation, and now ſticks hard upon my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, was diſobedience to my parents, in thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and commands their love and my intereſt put them upon laying before me, (to wit) the ſervice of that God, to whom my being and well-being was indebted, but careleſs of thoſe inſtructions, and my own good, I trampled upon their advice, and like the Swine diſregarded the pearl, not knowing the value of it, and wallowed in the mire and dirt of my own evil heart and affections, forſaking my Duties to God both in private and publick prayer, reading, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with other duties of his worſhip, which was the firſt cauſe that provoked God to leave me to my ſelf, and ſo conſequently to all the evils I have ſince fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: in the conſideration of which my conſcience flies in my face, and upbraids me with this great truth, that the breach was not on Gods part but mine, for if I had continued in thoſe ways and courſes, my parents by the inculcation of Scripture had taught me, and not truſted to my ſelf or my own manadgery, God would never have forſaken me, nor permitted me to fall into thoſe inconveniences I now ſink under the weight of. I left my parents about the age of thirteen, and betook my ſelf to a ſervice in <hi>Becconsfield</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks,</hi> where growing in years I grew in ſin, and day by day added guilt to guilt; to my former diſobedience of my parents and neglect of God I now joyned luſt and pride, thoſe two reigning and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive ſins, the root and beginning of all my future failings; to which as to the head ſpring I owe all the motions and gradations I have made hellwards; the ſtrength of which two ſins, eſpecially that of my luſt,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38451:3"/>the Devil that great deluder of ſouls made the bait of his temptations to enſnare &amp; keep me in the net of his Juriſdiction, wherein I then commenced and have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince continued a ſlave. How great the power of this ſin is when once it hath made an inroad upon Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity the bulwark againſt it, thoſe only know who feel the powerful operations thereof in themſelves, or behold it in the ſad inſtances and effectives of its ſtrength in others: from <hi>Becconsfield</hi> I removed to <hi>Wattleton</hi> in the ſame County to another ſervice which happened in a publick houſe, in which place being not fifteen years of age, I made my ſelf a proſtitute to thoſe luſts I had before that time only approved of, and was delighted with in the revolution of my thoughts; the remembrance of which ſin (at that time a moſt ſweet and delicious morſel to my palat) is now the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ingredient of my miſery: It is now I ſee how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully fair were all thoſe falſe apples of <hi>Sodom,</hi> my former pleaſures: Rottenneſs was lodged in the core, pollution in the touch, and deſtruction in the taſte thereof. From <hi>Wattleton</hi> I removed for <hi>London,</hi> but though I changed my reſidence, my heart was not changed, and I ſtill continued in thoſe courſes, the ſuggeſtions thereof and my own impure affections led me to, and grew more hardy and bold in my crimes; Sins I formerly trembled at the commitment of, I could now meet without the leaſt reluctancy or tremu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, ſwallowing greedily my own poyſon, eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it my pleaſanteſt food and choiceſt proviſion, ſuch as wherein neither danger of ſurfetting my ſoul or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying my body was ever in the leaſt to be feared: yet at ſome time the Devil though his power was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38451:4"/>in me, could not ſtop the mouth of that rebel to him my conſcience, but it would tell me how great a criminal I was to my ſelf, and ſlave to an unjuſt maſter in the courſes I proſecuted: this in the heat and vigour of my injoyments would ſometimes quell and damp them; but like a ſickly Qualm, the health of my pleaſure would quickly rid my ſtomack thereof; the Devil turning Phiſitian (as at ſuch times he was always readieſt to do) and adminiſtring a pill or doſe of falſe comfort, to relieve me. From <hi>London</hi> I return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to my parents in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> where after ſome ſhort ſtay with them, I removed to <hi>Cheſham,</hi> little delighting in the company of thoſe whereby I might have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifited in relation to my ſoul, knowing that that would put me upon bridling my luſt, too great a ſelf-denial to be thought on with patience: At <hi>Cheſham</hi> I alighted into a Family where I lived about two years, one year and three quarters of which I lived in the conſtant commitment of whoredom with my Maſter, who was at that time a married man, and by him I had a Childe which is yet living, to bring which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, and to cover that ſin I had committed, I was removed for <hi>London,</hi> where after ſome ſhort time being delivered of the burthen of my ſin and ſhame, and the iſſue thereof provided for, I went in the quality of a wet-Nurſe into a very honeſt and Religious Family in <hi>Roderith,</hi> where I might if my own evil heart had not been fooliſh and deſperately wicked, been warned both by their example and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to other courſes then I did then or ſince follow; but when once God gives up a perſon or people to a reprobate ſence and ſtate, neither examples can allure
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38451:4"/>nor precepts oblige them to what may be for their own benefit; ſo beſotted and fooliſh a creature is man in that ſtate, that though he knows his own good, yet he either neglects or diſowns it as a trifle, nay, many times eſteems it as an injury to be put in minde thereof. From <hi>Roderith</hi> I removed into <hi>Frogmorton-ſtreet,</hi> where likewiſe in a very honeſt Family I was well placed, wherein <hi>I</hi> obſerve the goodneſs of God in affording me thoſe means of return to himſelf which my own evil heart at all times eſchewed; and how well might it now have been with me had God given me grace to have followed the counſell and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Miſtreſſe in whoſe ſervice <hi>I</hi> then lived; how many harſh reflections of a guilty conſcience, how many beſmeared cheeks and ſwollen eyes, and above all how many ſins, beſides this for which <hi>I</hi> muſt go hence and be ſeen no more, might have been ſpared thereby? In this ſervice though often warned againſt it <hi>I</hi> became acquainted with a perſon (whoſe Name though <hi>I</hi> might have cauſe, yet having forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven all the world, <hi>I</hi> ſhall not mention) who did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail upon me to the committing of that crime, the iſſue whereof hath juſtly contracted my days; by him <hi>I</hi> found my ſelf with childe, and upon ſome difference thereabouts with my aforeſaid Miſtreſſe, <hi>I</hi> parted thence, and went to live in a very reputable Family within the County of <hi>Surrey,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> ſaw the Service of God duely and faithfully adminiſtred, and every minute met with thoſe examples of good and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous living, that had <hi>I</hi> not been hardned to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree, <hi>I</hi> ſhould certainly have taken notice of it: But ſo ſtrong was the infatuation of the devil upon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38451:5"/>me at that time, that <hi>I</hi> grew hardened under the means of mercy, and the more God extended his kindeneſs to me, the leſſe good was wrought on me thereby; the ſun-beams of his mercy ſhone upon my clay'y heart only to its hardening, whilſt the hearts of others were melted like wax into a through-obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of thoſe commands <hi>I</hi> trampled upon and ſpurn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at: In this condition the devil had brought me and kept me, the iſſue of my body ſtill growing more mature, and <hi>I</hi> ſenceleſs of my own folly, more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the ſhame of the matter towards me, and amongſt my acquaintance, then the crime <hi>I</hi> had committed againſt the great God of heaven and earth, whoſe holy commands <hi>I</hi> had ſo repeatedly violated: The time of my delivery growing nearer each day then other, <hi>I</hi> had ſeveral thoughts of providing for the infant, and accordingly had taken a room, but the temptations of the devil overpower'd all good reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in me, and when the hour of bringing forth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, leaving the principles of Chriſtianity, and laying aſide the bowels and tenderneſſe of a Mother, forgetting the laws of God and nature, and diſregard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the checks of my own conſcience, <hi>I</hi> baſely and inhumanly ſtrangled the iſſue of my womb, and ſtrove to conceal as well the ſin as ſhame of this horrid Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the eyes of the world, by hiding the infant in my Trunk, ſo great, ſo crying a ſin, that were the blood of Chriſt, or the mercy of God of leſs value then it is, I ſhould utterly diſpair of ever obtaining a pardon therefore. <hi>Lord! what a wretched creature is man di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted of thy grace! how are all thoſe noble faculties where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou didſt at firſt endow him, disfigured? his higheſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38451:5"/>perfect madneſs, his greateſt mercy extreameſt cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, all his actions, fooliſh and beſottedly ignorant; the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills engine to ruine and deſtroy as well his own as others ſouls: even ſuch a creature Lord am I; and can I ever hope to ſee thy face? can thy holineſs admit ſo vile and impure a wretch as my ſelf to be in thy preſence? I that have ſo often affronted thy Majeſty, trampled upon thy honour, abuſed thy mercy; I that am a Whore, a Murtherer, a Lyer, the very worſt of thy creation, can I ever expect thy mercy? The Laws of men have left no</hi> Aſylum <hi>for me to fly to, and wilt thou, oh Lord, tender thy boſom to receive and preſerve me? infinit is thy mercy and thy ſons interceſſion, therefore will I not deſpair.</hi> This crime thus commited, Juſtice hath overtaken me for, and before an earthly Tribunal; I have received a moſt juſt ſentence therefore, and am now under the dayly expectation of taking my laſt farewell of the world, and ſhaking hands with all the follies and troubles thereof, which leads me to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing premiſed, <hi>viz.</hi> an account of my preſent thoughts in relation to the condition my ſins have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced me to; the which to methodize, for the benefit of others, though it is my earneſt deſire, yet am I ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible the task is difficult, conſidering the confuſions and diſturbances thereof, the many mixtures of fears and hopes ariſing from the different conſiderations of my former miſcariages and preſent but imperfect aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances; wherefore I ſhall firſt of all in general lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you a draft, though but an imperfect one, of my ſaid thoughts upon my firſt conviction, and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſhew you, how God hath pleaſed to work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me in order to the ſettlement of thoſe confuſions I was then diſturbed with: wherefore in the firſt place,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38451:6"/>no ſooner had I received ſentence of Death from an Earthly throne, but it put me in minde of that ſentence I was ſhortly to receive in the higheſt Heavens from that God, and for thoſe crimes, whereby during all my life I had ſo highly provoked his anger and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance againſt me; which conſideration filled me with terrors of the Almighty, and made me cry out under the weight of my burthen, that it was greater then I could bear: Hell-fire flaſht in my face, and the devil who formerly hurried me preſumtuouſly to perſiſt in my impieties, now turned the drift of his temtations to force me to deſpair, making uſe of the memory of my former crimes, in all the black aggravations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to inhance my infidelities, terrifying me with the juſtice of God, who before he had repreſented as a merciful father, ready and eaſie to forgive his failing children, he now ſhapes as an angry Judge bound to condemn offenders: In this condition never was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery greater then the thoughts of that chance I was and am ſhortly to make; neither ever had any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a more perfect portraiture of the uglineſs of ſin then at this time I met with: Imagine but then how little pleaſure, or rather how great was my torture in the revolutions of the idle expence of my former hours and days, of my former pleaſant and as <hi>I</hi> then thought innocent paſtimes: Theſe were my torment, but how much more, how exceedingly and inconceiveably greater was the thoughts of my diſobedience to my parents, my neglect of God in all the duties of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, my exceſſive pride, my repeated and continued whoredomes, and above all my unnatural deſtruction of the off-ſpring of my own body: Theſe were as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38451:6"/>mountains of Lead under which helpleſs and hopeleſs I lay overwhelmed; my comfort came ſlowly upon me, and though ſometimes a Beam of hope would ſhine in upon my ſoul from the conſideration of the merits and blood of Chriſt (my dear Lord and Saviour) yet the ſame was imediately clouded by the revolution of the thoughts premiſed, and now it was I found how hard the work of repentance, (let the world paſs what ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents they pleaſe thereon) was to bring about, how many were the conflicts with the fleſh and the Devil that <hi>I</hi> grapled with, how many bitter ſighs and groans, how many fears and terrors was <hi>I</hi> wrapped up in ere <hi>I</hi> could bring my ſelf to a ſerious and hearty repentance for my paſt crimes? It is true, the condition <hi>I</hi> was in, under a ſentence of Death, made me ſorry, that <hi>I</hi> had committed the offence that had brought me thereto, yet the fear of death more then the greatneſs of the crime againſt God was the cauſe of that ſorrow, and had not that ſentence been paſt upon me, <hi>I</hi> fear my heart would never have been affected with that ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: Whence <hi>I</hi> would beg and requeſt of all to whom theſe lines ſhall come, that they take it as the advice of a dying woman, who being nearer, can ſee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the things of another world, then thoſe who ſtand at a diſtance thence, that they would not deferr the great work of repentance, till they come within proſpect of eternity, which every day brings them nearer to then other. Thus much in general; <hi>I</hi> ſhall deſcend to particulars, in ſhewing you, how God hath pleaſed to work upon me in order to the ſettlement of my thoughts under theſe confuſions <hi>I</hi> was at preſent under, wherein notwithſtanding all thoſe ſuggeſtions
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38451:7"/>the Devil and my own evil heart did terrifie me with, <hi>I</hi> have found that God is a merciful father to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and returning ſinners though juſt againſt obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate offenders: To his free grace in Chriſt Jeſus my Lord <hi>I</hi> attribute all the comfort <hi>I</hi> have and muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, here and hereafter: Wherefore in the firſt place I ſhall ſhew you, that God hath been pleaſed by a graciouſly powerful hand to work upon me, in turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me to a perfect deteſtation of my ſins, more in that they are and have been an affront to his Majeſty, then the Cauſe of that temporal Death <hi>I</hi> am to ſuffer therefore. To make out this, <hi>I</hi> am to acquaint you, that having received my Sentence on Thurſday night, <hi>I</hi> continued in great confuſions as aforeſaid for two or three days, and though a good Friend who tarried moſt part of the time with me, aſſiſted me with his advice and prayers, yet could <hi>I</hi> not bring my ſelf to ſo ſetled a temper, but that my fears clouded my hopes, and deprived me of thoſe comforts, which otherwiſe and under other Conſiderations I might have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the devil being all this time buſie in ſtirring that mud, my own evil heart had too readily raiſed. On the Munday following <hi>I</hi> was viſited by a Miniſter of worth within the City of <hi>London,</hi> who after ſeveral queſtions by him propounded, and threats of the Law againſt ſuch criminals as my ſelf were laid open, <hi>I</hi> began to ſee my tranſgreſſions, without that vizard the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had generally masked them with; the uncomely ſhape whereof, did adminiſter that amazement to me, which was the firſt ſtep of that abhorrency <hi>I</hi> have ſince conceived againſt them, and no wonder that poor creatures are ſo much deceived, in their opinion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38451:7"/>of ſin, conſidering the ſpecious advantage under which a repreſentation by that evil one is made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: the which till the purblinde eyes of man come to the neareſt view thereof (to wit,) in a puniſhment therefore, or by Gods ſpeciall grace, he can never diſcern it in its true proportion or colour, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues under a fancied deceit, that there is in ſin ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what exceedingly amiable, profitable, or reputable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, without which he could never live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that injoyment of happineſs and content, as the ſame would at all times afford him: Thus (with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands in the like caſe with me) I was always deluded, and on this account did <hi>I</hi> run on in thoſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful courſes whoſe end is a ſcertain'd deſtruction, as <hi>I</hi> to my coſt have found it; but the time is now come, that the vail is drawn aſide, and <hi>I</hi> begin to conſider the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide and bottom of thoſe crimes which before that time lay covered under a ſpecious and fair <hi>ſuperficies:</hi> and thereby came to a diſcovery of what before <hi>I</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did really poſſeſs my ſelf with: <hi>I</hi> now conſider'd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſin a breach of Gods Law, and a provocation of that vengeance that might every moment have ſpurn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me into an abyſſe of miſery, and turned me out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe who are weeping, wailing, and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their teeth, in the pit of perdition, from whence to the throne of grace and mercy no appeal can be: and that it was the exceeding patience and forbearance of God that he had ſpared ſo vile, ſo impure a wretch as my ſelf, ſo long under ſuch continued and repeated impieties, to violate his laws, and contemn his moſt Sacred and auguſt authority: which conſiderations, as they raiſed my deteſtation and hatred againſt ſin, ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38451:8"/>did they inhance the value and price of Gods mercy, the two firſt ſtones to that great work of converſion, which <hi>I</hi> hope God has in me the unworthyeſt ſubject of his choice in ſome meaſure graciouſly effected, as arguments of which my own heart gives me theſe five evidences, which laid together confirm the ſame to my comfort.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That under the ſence of my Sin, <hi>I</hi> confeſſe and acknowledg my ſelf deſervedly a condemned creature, unleſs the application of the blood of Chriſt my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and his interceſſion, at the throne of grace, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the free love of God, ſhall repeal the ſentence againſt me.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>I</hi> do throughly and from my heart deteſt and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor ſin in general, and ſhould God pleaſe to lengthen out my days, <hi>I</hi> ſhould continue my reſolutions of a through repentance and reformation of life, forſaking all courſes contrary to Gods holy word and Law.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>I</hi> find in my Spirit a delight in reading and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, things <hi>I</hi> formerly omitted and eſchewed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A fiduciary expectation of forgiveneſs from God, of all paſt crimes, through Jeſus Chriſt, freely relying and repoſing my ſelf on him for Salvation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>I</hi> do freely and from my heart forgive all the world, and bear to none the leaſt ill will.</p>
            <p>Which conſiderations, are the ground of that hope, that balmes my wounded heart, and cordialls my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying ſpirits, under the great change <hi>I</hi> am ſo ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make: To diſcourſe of which is the next, and laſt thing <hi>I</hi> have to ſay, and would to God <hi>I</hi> could now lay by all the cloggs of fleſh, and earth, and mount up upon the wings of faith, into ſuch a ſtate as the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38451:8"/>Apoſtle was when he deſired to be diſſolved, and be with Chriſt; but alas! how many difficulties, am <hi>I</hi> now to graple with, what Mountains of oppoſition ſtand in my way, too high and great, to travel o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: before me <hi>I</hi> ſee a fair Heaven, inviting and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring the aſpect to an enjoyment thereof, but diſtant from my Eye, by depth ſeemingly ſtormy and impaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, into which <hi>I</hi> am fearfull and loath to lanch, fearing the weight of my ſins, ſhould ſink me, ere <hi>I</hi> could compaſſe the other ſhore: <hi>I</hi> look back, and ſee my former habitations in the fleſh, which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and cuſtome had rendred pleaſant to me, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined and deſtroyed, nothing commendable in it for my ſtay, or entertainment: my familiars forgetting deſpiſing, and forſaking me, under diſgrace with all, through my own crime and folly, and a Judicial ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity upon me, to ſpeed my way; in this caſe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, comfort flys me on all ſides, if <hi>I</hi> look, down <hi>I</hi> am ſtartled at my own ill repreſentations and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; to Heaven therefore is my beſt and laſt refuge, whether when <hi>I</hi> extend my Eyes, my ſoul breaths our, in deſires to this or the like effect. <hi>(Lord thou knoweſt my paſt frailties and preſent perplexities, be thou my ſtreerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to guide me, through this Sea of tears to thy ſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee and thy aſſiſtance, I ſhould immediately ſplit upon the Rocks of deſpair, or ſink into the Gulph of infidelity, where I ſhould ever remain, without hope to bring my Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt Soul into the Haven of thy mercy, which ſtands at all times open for repenting and believing ſinners.)</hi> To ſuch breathings of my Soul, God is ſometimes pleaſed to give the anſwer of his ſpirit, in the return of peace, at which time, as the Sun that hath long lain hid in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38451:9"/>a dark Ecclipſe, darts forth its refreſhing rays, to the comfort of beholders, ſo from that black ſcene of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, under which my breaſt is troubled, radiates a joy unſpeakable, and ſo great, that I cannot expreſs it, but in the bleſſed effects thereof, which leads me to the deſpiſing the world, in the greateſt pleaſures of it, and mounts up my Soul ſo high, above the nether Sphere, that when <hi>I</hi> view it, methinks it ſeems ſo little and deſpicable a ſpot, what were it to be purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the rate, of one of the leaſt crimes <hi>I</hi> ever was guilty of, it would be unmercifully over rated; and in this condition, imagine whether <hi>I</hi> have any minde or deſire, to take up a habitation therein, and neglect thoſe divine manſions, where cares and troubles, and above all, ſin is a ſtranger; Manſions where God and Angells inhabit, and enjoy themſelves, in a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Halelujah</hi> and harmony, to which I am a going; it is then I can kiſs the halter that ſhall ſtrangle me, and the hand that ſhall diſpatch me to theſe enjoyments, accounting my ſelf happy in my troubles, and bleſt in my miſeries: But thus it fares not at all times with me, but fleſh will get the upper hand, and ſometimes drag me down to Earth, and keep me from mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heavenward, which as it is againſt my peace, ſo likewiſe much againſt my will and prayers to God, that he would pleaſe to prevent it: Thus have <hi>I</hi> gone through, with what in the firſt part of this Diſcourſe was premiſed, <hi>(viz.)</hi> an Account of my Life and crime, for which <hi>I</hi> received my ſentence of Death, as alſo the ſence of my condition, upon conſideration of both: it remains now only upon the whole, That the Reader would candidly interpret, of what theſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38451:9"/>lines have contained, and make uſe of them as a warning, from running on in thoſe ways, the Devil and my own heart hath led me in, whoſe end will be certainly bitter, to all that purſue the ſame; which that the ſame uſe may be made thereof, ſhall be to the laſt gaſp, the prayer of <hi>Dorothy Lillingſtone.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="supplement">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:38451:10"/>
            <head>A Supplement to the Preceding Diſcourſe.</head>
            <p>IT is certainly the higheſt Judgement, as well as the greateſt miſery of this Age, that the frequent and many Examples which every day preſent themſelves, to the view of the World, ſhould work ſo little upon the Inhabitants thereof, to turn them from their evill ways to repentance, and make them forſake thoſe courſes, whoſe end will be aſſuredly greivous to them; one main reaſon whereof may be this, That ſo few amongſt the many, that are by Gods Juſtice ſet forth, as Examples to others, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded as ſuch, but are eſteemed as the worſt of creatures, and ſo not worthy the ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of ſuch, that think themſelves paramount, above the fear or danger of falling into ſuch crimes, as brought thoſe to their deſerved ends; little conſidering the deceitfullneſs of their own hearts, and the proneneſſe of every one of us, if once deſerted by God, to fall into the worſt of crimes, or elſe the Example intended by God, is ſtiffled by the ſufferers ſilence, or the reputation of Relations, who are not to expoſe their friends failings, and diſgracefull ends to the World; To prevent both which falſe uſes of Gods providence, the preceding diſcourſe was intended and penned, wherein the truth of the Relation commends the ſame to the Reader: And I ſhall ſay but little Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional thereto, only requeſt that into whoſe hands
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38451:10"/>this ſmall Treatiſe may fall, they would make this treble uſe of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſee the deceitfulneſſe of the heart of man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The great miſcheifs that ariſe, from the ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly little and inconſiderable beginnings of ſin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To take this as an Example, to warn others from truſting to their own hearts, or venturing upon ſin in the leaſt degree thereof, leſt thereby they may be brought to thoſe miſchiefs, which be certainly deſtructive to the purſuers: This only by the way.</p>
            <p>I now proceed, to give an Account of <hi>Dorothy Lillingſtone,</hi> ſince the end of her own Narrative: The day before her death, being with her, I made an inquiry in what condition ſhe found her ſelf; and whether ſhe was ſettled, and diſpoſed for the great work ſhe was the next day to go through. To which ſhe anſwered me, that it was no eaſy work to dye, but ſuch wherein the greateſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties imaginable, were to be encountred, and ſhe had upon the firſt thoughts of the ſame ſo found it, but through the grace of God, ſhe had been ſo wrought upon, that ſhe could then eaſily, and willingly meet and embrace it, in the worſt of its appearances, or words to this effect; after which, upon further diſcourſe, I inquired upon what
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38451:11"/>grounds ſhe became willing to dye, who had been formerly ſo terrified thereat, to which ſhe replied, God had been ſo mercifull to her, and made her ſencible of the greatneſs of her crimes, whereby ſhe had been wrought to a real Repentance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and thereby was under the great hopes of forgiveneſs, through the blood and merits of Chriſt, her deareſt Lord and Saviour, the which temper of minde, ſhe was further incouraged to, through the certainty of her Death, which every minute ſhe was put in mind of, by the ſight of her Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin and ſhrowd, (then being in the Chamber with her;) after which I began through the great hopes I perceived of her, to give her conſolation and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement in her preſent temper of minde, and aſſured her, that her ſins, though never ſo many and great (as ſhe had confeſt hers to be) were not ſufficient to ſtand between God and her hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs; for that Gods Mercy was infinite, and her iniquities in the higheſt ſum, but finite. I then enquired of her, how ſhe intended to ſpend the enſuing night, to which ſhe anſwered, ſhe had taken her laſt farewell of her bed, and did intend to ſet up in Prayer and Reading all night; againſt which, conſidering her weakneſſe, I diſſwaded her, telling her her ſtrength could not bear it out; to which ſhe ſuddenly anſwered, Perſwade me not againſt it, for I am reſolved this night to ſerve my God, though in weakneſſe, and I am encouraged to hope he will accept thereof; After which being about to leave her, ſhe only deſired me to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38451:11"/>her a little Bible (having then only a great one by her) to carry in her hand the next day to the place of Execution, ſaying, ſhe would there reade a Chapter and a Pſalm, and in a few words give warning to the Spectators of her death, and the cauſes of it, and ſo commend her ſelf and ſoul to God in prayer. After which I left her to God: And the next Morning I came to her early, and rejoyced to finde her in a very quiet temper of minde, ſubmitting to the Juſtice of God in the great work ſhe was that day to undergo; the which ſhe told me ſhe was encouraged unto, in that God had pleaſed to lift up the Light of his Countenance upon her, and give her ſome aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his love to her (notwithſtanding her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold crimes) in and through Chriſt: and that now ſhe could leave the World willingly, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting thoſe happineſſes in the place whether ſhe was going, that all the greatneſſes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, could be met with in her abode here, could never afford her; I then enquired whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to her former deſire this Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſhould be expoſed to the World, to which ſhe anſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d me, ſhe was very deſirous it might, and that I would cauſe the ſame to be Printed, ſaying, ſhe had ſpoken to ſeverall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters therein, who had commended her former thoughts, in relation thereto, and that her friends did expect it: but above all, ſhe hoped it might be for the publick benefit, to warn others from crimes that were her deſtruction, ſaying, ſhe hop'd
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38451:12"/>that her ruine might ſtand as a monument of Braſſe, to give notice to the world, of the evil and pernicious work of Sin. After which I left her, and met her again at the place of Execution, where ſhe behaved her ſelf Exemplarily penitent, amongſt the number of thoſe who ſuffered with her, and were obſtinately hardened under the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Death; at which time ſhe read the 7th. Chapter of <hi>Job,</hi> and the 51. Pſalm, and addreſſed her ſelf to God in prayer, deſiring the ſpectators there preſent to pray for her, and to take her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample as a means to deter them from the courſes that brought her to that deſerved and ſhameful end, which ſhe was now come at that place and time to accompliſh: After which ſhe quietly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendered her ſoul to the Almighty, and her body to Execution; which work being over, her friends removed her Corps in a Coach in order to her Buriall: and accordingly was decently interred in in the Pariſh Church of St. <hi>George's Southwark.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:38451:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
